Una Producción de Reclusion Films
Executive Producers
Associate Producers
Produced By
Director de Fotografía
Original Score
Additional Music
Directed and Edited By
Éxtasis del Orden
Los Maestros de Tetris
It is estimated that two out of every three Americans have played Tetris.
Tetris es un juego de habilidad
Seven blocks of different shapes descend from the top of the screen.
The player must arrange them to form and clear horizontal lines.
Success is measured by the number of lines cleared,
and the total number of points scored.
As the player clears more lines, the pieces fall faster.
The faster the pieces fall, the more points are scored.
When the pieces reach the top of the screen, the game is over.
Russian computer scientist Alexey Pajitnov invented Tetris in 1984 on an Electronika 60.
In the years that followed, the game exploded in popularity,
and was ported to virtually every computer and console on the market.
In 1989, Nintendo released Tetris for the Game Boy and the Nintendo Entertainment System,
selling nearly 40 million copies, and bringing the game to the masses.
In 1990, Nintendo chose Tetris as the central game in the largest video game tournament the world had ever seen,
the Nintendo World Championships.
Un niño de Texas de 14 años llamado Thor ganó.
Nintendo's Tetris came to be viewed as the definitive version of the game,
its secrets and mysteries fascinating the best players in the decades to come.
Every successful game ends with the same message to the player.
YOU ARE A TETRIS MASTER.
This is the story of the people who truly mastered the game.
Midwest Gaming Classic: "The Midwest's Largest All-Encompassing Electronic Gaming Event!"
Un pequeño torneo de Tetris en Milwaukee, Wisconsin
I've done nothing but play Tetris for many many years,
Ben Mullen / World Record Holder / Most Lines (296)
and now I'm here because I heard about a Tetris competition,
and I'm here hopefully to win it.
I mean, I began Tetris really when I was... a kid,
but I used to take statistics of every single game I played
and write down whether I had... a cup of coffee beforehand or something like that
to kind of see... what would make me play Tetris the best.
And I found out, that, actually, exactly one half hour before you have...
after you have some coffee, you play the best.
Otro pequeño torneo de Tetris en Portland, Oregon.
...top eight, we're moving to the Super Nintendo version, where you actually play against each other
Robin Mihara / Organizador Torneo de Tetris
and every time you get a tetris, it sends garbage to the other person.
*gasp* What just happened!
- Ooh, the most painful misdrop in Ashley's life!
Veamos si puede sobrevivir!
Ohh... I'm sorry. Tetris is not fair, folks.
I've got to get it together.
I'm still in it, by a little. Just a... frickin' hair's breadth.
Ben was just informed that in the final match, the players won't be allowed to rotate the pieces.
This is considered a very unusual style of play.
Ben wins with a score of 2586 points.
This is what 15 years of playing one game and one game only will get you,
in a tournament, somewhere, and a documentary thereafter.
It's all about Tetris!
It goes a lot faster than that, if you're really good.
We have a new low!
53 puntos!
She came in and asked for a glass of blood.
Malin clears a little space, gets ready for her long bar...
Tetris! Look at this comeback.
Ooh, Malin takes it by a landslide!
Your champion, Malin Nylander.
And that's it everybody, please go home!
The Portland Retro Gaming Expo
So this one is three...
- Yeah
...you got three more for five...
...if I bought all three of them, would you go to four for each?
- Sure!
You're a big Tetris fan?
Yeah, we are finding the best Tetris player in the world.
And we always had wondered why the biggest game in the world --
well, it's probably the most played game ever --
didn't have a champion,
and games like Pac-Man had Billy Mitchell,
and Asteroids now has John McAllister,
and Tetris is possibly played even more than that,
John McAllister / Campeon Mundial de Asteroids
and I decided to find the best Tetris players in the world and play them in a contest.
It's the only video game that can be described as perfect, right?
Because, how would you improve it?
What, add a shape? Take away a shape?
The shapes in the games are called tetraminoes.
Alexey Pajitnov / Creador de Tetris
It comes from Greece, Tetra means four in Greece... four.
Board game which kind of was the inspiration of my game was the puzzle called pentaminoes.
You know that chess is, or used to be Olympic sport.
So, it's ok for mental activity to be a matter of sportive competition.
I believe that Tetris may well be the first virtual sport.
Henk Rogers / CEO, The Tetris Company
If I was going to practice to be the smartest or the fastest thinker in the world,
would I play football?
I don't think so.
I would play Tetris.
For months I have been searching for these CRT televisions.
They're kind of hard to find, but we're here at this thrift store and we found a motherload.
There's about 10 in there.
Despite being based in Portland, Oregon,
Robin decides to hold his tournament in Los Angeles in an effort to draw more people.
He hopes that if he can get the best players involved and crown a champion,
he will have done his part to legitimize Tetris as a professional sport.
Well, I'm pretty happy with this.
No more Internet scoreboards, no more second chances,
just a good old-fashioned face-to-face tournament for the ages.
It's the Tetris showdown of the century, we're joined live by Robin Mihara.
So, the world championship, what kind of competition are we talking about here?
We're talking about the classic NES Tetris.
Tetris is probably the most-played video game of all time.
It's an addicting game and it's stolen millions of hours from millions of people.
The champion has never been crowned, and I made it my goal
to seek out and find a world champion.
Are you a big fan? 'Cause I know when I play I like to stack them up all on one side,
and then you get one of those long four ones,
'cause it's such a good pay-off when you get the four, the four lines...
Yeah, I do enjoy that maneuver.
The long bar to get the tetris, it's pretty solid.
Tetris is a game of decisions, each one affecting the next
at speeds of up to two decisions per second.
The Tetris master strives to make the right decision,
every single time, up to 700 times per game.
To do this, the Tetris master must maintain focus.
The four line clear, called a tetris, scores the most points.
The master relentlessly pursues tetrises.
This is done by building a wall and leaving a well.
The long bar completes the tetris.
The probability of getting a long bar at any given moment is about one out of seven.
The long bar is the most important piece in the game.
An extended period without it is known as a drought.
A long bar drought is the most dreaded occurence in NES Tetris.
Robin is about to experience a drought.
Drought Count:
To survive the drought Robin is forced to start burning lines off the top of his wall.
That was a drought.
A long bar drought of 40 pieces is deadly to the average player.
Portland, Oregon
I think I've narrowed down what I consider to be the top Tetris players in the world.
This is where they live and I've decided that I'm going to hold a massive contest,
invite them all and come out of there knowing who the best Tetris player in the world is.
Once I found Twin Galaxies -- they keep the world records for all video games --
Twin Galaxies / The Official Electronic Scoreboard / Since 1981 The worldwide Authority on Player Ranking
it dawned on me that not only had several people been playing this game
ever since it came out 22 years ago,
but a lot of people have been taking it very, very seriously.
Quite a few years ago, it all started with just a mysterious tape popping up.
Kelly Flewin / Twin Galaxies NES Referee
Hm, a couple hundred thousand on Tetris, well this should definitely be interesting
and I had no idea it was gonna snowball so exponentially as it has.
Dana Wilcox kind of out of nowhere just posted this score a month ago.
I don't know very much about her, but she's from the Oakland area.
Oakland, California
I mean, I had no idea that that was even... that Twin Galaxies even existed
until my friend was all "dude, check out King of Kong" and I saw King of Kong and I was like,
Dana Wilcox / 4th All-Time / Most Points (722,065)
you know, it's on.
Like, whoa, that exists?! And then I start checking out Tetris on there and all the scores were crap.
When I was a kid, my mom got pretty good.
We had this like, this dry-erase whiteboard and it would say what chore you had to do that week
and in the top corner it would always say the reigning highest Tetris score
which my mom held for two months and then I wiped her off the board and that was it.
Do you remember what that score was?
I think it was like 151-ish [thousands].
The next one I remember was just like a 624 [thousands].
I took a polaroid at the TV, like, 624, check it out bitches!
You know, I couldn't leave the screen on for that long.
Freeze! It's like an Etch A Sketch that you freeze in time, like,
no one ever touches the TV again.
Which maybe I would do if I maxed it out.
Jesse Kelkar at one point held the world record for lines.
Sherman Oaks, California
I wanna say somewhere between 3.5 and 4 feet long,
so he's almost doubled in size since we got him.
Jesse Kelkar / 2nd All-Time / Most Lines (291)
Well, let's see, my mom would have been the one to bring the game into the house.
She brought it home one night and the whole family sat down and started playing.
And she had a natural knack for it and I turned out to have a natural knack for it
and so it would turn into competitions between me and my mom a lot.
And I would do my school work, because she wouldn't let me on the Nintendo before my scho --
and yes, she would check it, 'cause she was not giving up that Nintendo for anything.
My husband, you know, goes onto Google and he finds Twin Galaxies' website.
This is like, a serious website and they track this stuff and they'd been doing it since the 80's
and so I sat and I played and I got to level 29.
For the first time I saw level 29 and I went "whoa."
And I finally got to 291 and I was like, ok, you know, this is enough Tetris,
I'll stick with 291, let's see how it goes.
And I got the certificate where I have, you know, I am a world record holder and whatnot
Video Game World Champion / Jesse Kelkar
and then I think Ben came in about three months later and just went
"no, I'm not having this 291 I'm gonna go with 294" and I went "oh..."
Ben Mullen is the world record holder for the most number of lines at 296.
Which means, incredibly he was able to score six lines
into what everyone considers the death-screen.
Minneapolis, Minnesota
Lines in tetris have a real elegance to them
Ben Mullen / World Record Holder / Most Lines (296)
if you get really good at getting a lot of lines every time.
In high-school I was to the point where I could average over 270 lines per game.
Which, when you average in some bad games, I'm getting to level 29 nearly every time.
So this is just a quick game I played to show that I'm still capable of getting to level 29.
And I may or may not get there, because I can't remember
if the piece I just dropped gets me there or not.
So let's see, wish it luck.
Oh yeah, it does, ok, that's level 29, that was really quick.
But level 29 does tend to kill you, so I'm dead.
In high school I got an 820,000 and that's a pretty good score even today.
So I started watching and people like Harry Hong and whatnot would come along
and they were scoring, but they were scoring way beneath what I had done.
So I've got an arrogant attitude like, I'm number 1, no one can touch me.
Harry Hong's nothing, everybody's nothing, that's the attitude I had,
so I wasn't trying to make myself better.
And Harry Hong was.
Los Angeles, California
I made it a goal to get the max, like, I had to.
Harry Hong / Co-World Record Holder / Most Points (999,999)
I'd say four years... it was a pretty long time.
I just believed, I just made myself believe that I was capable of doing it.
For the past couple of years there's been a leapfrogging situation
where everyone was trying to be the first person to ever max out the game.
There are two paramount achievements within NES tetris largely dismissed as unattainable.
The first is the max-out: a perfect score of 999,999 points.
With only a six-digit score counter, this is the highest possible score.
The master strives to score the max before reaching the level 29 kill-screen,
a level so fast that it is believed impossible to survive.
To reach the max before hitting the kill-screen, the master must play perfectly,
scoring tetrises at least 60% of the time.
Well, I didn't really reflect on the fact that there's only so many lines to work with.
So I had to fit more and more perfection into that same space.
No one ever thought that there would be a max-out.
That's pushing the realms of feasibility, and...
Lo and behold! A little while later, suddenly Harry pulls out some more magic from his hat
And... poof!
At that night when I got the max, I checked my score, I just glanced at it real quick
It was around... I believe it was in the high 960 thousands.
And... I knew I had to get a Tetris like, within the next, like, five lines.
The pieces didn't come out... I had to really think quickly on where to put the pieces at that time.
I made like two second, like last... maybe like last millisecond decisions.
So I had to like maneuver like really quickly.
I just dropped the controller, 'cause I was done, you know?
I dropped the controller and then I just yelled, I just yelled. It was like 1:30 in the morning
I'd saved a bottle of Johnny Walker just for that occasion. I've had that bottle for two years.
Yeah, that night we all took a shot of that and it was a good night, yeah.
That made me like, alright that's it, I'm maxing it out. Harry Hong is my hero.
'Cause before that, honestly, I had started, kind of like, in my own solitary Tetris world
QUIERO CREER
wondering if it was possible.
Harry did it first. Jonas actually claimed that he had done it before Harry
but he didn't have the appropriate video.
I gotta show you the technique, that has really kinda put me over the edge.
Jonas Neubauer / Co-World Record Holder / Most Points (999,999)
And it is, like, the eyes.
I've got like the eyes, like, I can split it out and check the next button, right?
Sometimes you need an advantage.
The first time I maxed it out, I just... it really... weird thing.
You have this goal, and you max it out, it's 1AM,
you have no camera, you have no way to... put this on film
So on my birthday, last year, in 2009, April 19th,
I saw that Harry had, you know, given me the birthday present of usurping me first to the title.
And so, you know, I didn't wanna see that on my birthday.
That kinda motivated me, I was like, I need to do this.
The first video was a level 18 max-out with no sound.
And... the initial reaction was, because there was no sound, it seemed like I had something to hide.
The second one was a level 19 max-out with my AT&T Tilt phone.
Right off the bat people kind of dismissed it because they couldn't see what was going on.
People comment on my video saying "it's fake", "it's a glitch", "he's cheating"
But I mean, in a way, I take that as a compliment, you know like
If they think it's really that impossible to play like that then... that's good for me.
Dude, the best on that YouTube... was reading all the comments of people that said like
"This is a fake video", "this is slowed down", "Oh! Look at", you know, "1:25 in"
Aaron Wright / Amigo de Jonas
"The camera glitches, it's clearly computer generated"
That's the whole folklore thing. That's the kind of Bigfoot photo type of situation
that I was trying to develop, actually.
The second paramount achievement within the game is passing the level 29 kill-screen and reaching level 30.
This is widely believed to be impossible because the pieces begin falling too quickly to reach the sides.
Ben Mullen has come the closest. His record of 296 lines, falling just four lines short of level 30.
Getting that record... It's really helpful if you're good at getting to level 29, a lot of times.
So I just got there over, and over, built up as high as I could.
Got tetrises and whatever I could do, and eventually I got six lines on there, and that's nuts in and of itself.
You gotta really build up pretty darn high to do that.
To get really far past that, you're gonna have to get pieces to the edge on level 29.
Which is, to me, just crazy.
There is a significant jump between level 28 and 29. It boggled me, you know?
I absolutely had to find out: who has seen level 30? Does level 30 exist?
Does it just keep going on forever?
There are two known strategies to reach level 30.
The first is to prepare a center well at the end of level 28, elimnating the need for pieces to reach the sides.
The second is to accelerate the movements of the pieces by rapidly vibrating the left thumb.
The big question is whether or not Thor is going to participate.
He has claimed to get past the death-screen of level 29 into 30.
Which is very hard to believe, once you've seen the speed of 29.
He, I believe, has maxed the game out at the age of 14. I never saw it.
Max-Out / 999,999
I don't know if anyone did, but I have no reason not to believe him.
He was the greatest Tetris player in the world 20 years ago.
He beat over a million kids, and he beat us handily.
Robin Mihara knows Nintendo.
He recently returned from the Nintendo World Championships in Universal City California.
The key to success:
Hand-eye coordination.
You have to have an eagle eye, a finger that flies and hours, and hours of practice.
You know, three months of training, and hundreds and hundreds of lines mode, all invested into this one contest.
Welcome to Universal Studios, Hollywood. This is the playing field of the future.
The unprecedented 1990 Nintendo World Championships.
Nintendo had 12 massive trailer-trucks full of equipment  and it was touring around the country
Taking one winner from each city and then it was gonna play all the winners together in Hollywood, to crown a champion.
But after watching Thor play, he had the ability to vibrate the directional pad
so that the piece actually moved faster than the rest of us could move it.
It seems kind of unfair.
I ended up playing two of my better games and ended up taking third behind Thor who won it all.
Can I write "Damn you, Thor" or anything? He's the guy that beat me.
Yeah, do it, totally. Totally do it.
That's my quote.
The day that he won the national championships, I went to his room and talked to him for the first time.
And he said that, um, he had gotten to level 30. This is a quote of his:
"If you get past level 30, it's pretty easy to max it out."
And it was the first time I ever heard someone saying that maxing out Tetris was pretty easy.
I think, you know, in 1990 I was really obsessed with wanting to win that competition.
Trey Harrison / Former NWC Competitor
Hey hey -- proof I know Thor Aackerlund.
Thor / Trey
Hey there.
Thor won in Houston, which is where I went for the very first time
and I don't know if he had developed that multi-tap technique by then; by the end of the tour, he had done it.
He was really moving the pieces, left and right, faster than everyone.
What none of us practiced to doing was, vibrate our left thumb, and that's what Thor would do.
And he could get the piece to move left to right faster than all of us.
And if you watch, Thor's got a technique for his 10-second countdown to get the long bar.
He's playing all the way up there, and he's vibrating so fast that he can get it over his giant stack.
And he doesn't even get the long bar; he could've demolished the score.
This is the seven champs with Howard Phillips, the face of Nintendo in the 90's.
There was something about each of us that was a little off, like...
I have ADD and a couple of the guys were awkward and...
none of us were like... your every day guy, which is probably why we were in the house playing Nintendo for 10 hours a day.
Thor was kinda the guy where, it's like, you feared him but you didn't wanna be him.
Chris Tang / Multi-Platform / Gaming Champion
Thor at the 1992 Consumer Electronics Show
Thor would kinda come up to us as a, sort of like an outcast and he'd walk up and say:
The Master Gamer
"My name is Thor. I'm good at games"
And then, you know, we'd go to the arcade and, you know, Thor would be there and he'd walk up to us and he'd say:
"I'm Thor, I'm good at games"
You know? Is it an OCD thing? You know, it's like, some people who are, you know, prodigies sometimes
you know, have, a little bit of a thing to that.
I kind of demonized him as a child because he squashed my dreams
but now that I'm past that, I just wanna know who this guy is.
I feel like he was just like me, just a nerd.
We hung out like in the mid 90's and like played games together
After the Nintendo World Championships he kind of burned out on the fame.
There was a video someone must've recorded off a TV in the early 90's
and it was the home shopping network, the woman was selling Micro Machines
"Micro Machines" Racing Game / ...different Micro Machines (from sports cars to...
Thor Aackerlund / Campeón Mundial de Nintendo
32 different tracks to play with. There he is Thor. He's out Nintendo World Champ and he is over there having a ball.
I'm pleading with him. I'm sending him a Nintendo to practice, if he needs one.
But if he can truly get to level 30, that's probably the most difficult achievement in gaming history.
And he needs to get that on tape.
42 days until the tournament.
The specific game that's over... this has to do more with my wife.
Uh... the game that's over being the dating game, of which I was never successful, anyways
So I guess I never pushed start on that.
I didn't really seek a geeky guy, but I found out that I really enjoy the things that he did
and one of my life-long goals was to be able to solve a Rubik's cube. Ever since the 80's growing up.
And Ben taught me and so, we began falling in love and now we're married.
Any way that you can turn it has a number code or a space or a dash.
five, five, two, five, one, nine, eight, two...
Sometimes it gets stuck
I learned it, uh, for the specific purpose of impressing women, so...
Really?
- Yeah.
Okay.
Really.
I think we're all of one accord that we need to save the princess here.
At the end of Mario 3, I really believed that the appropriate way to beat that game or not beat that game,
was to have Bowser fall down his hole and then fall right down that hole behind him.
Just kill yourself.
Well, they had just such a struggle together and it feels just right for them to go down together.
Cheapens the experience to just beat Bowser and listen to a show tune.
I like all games that end like Tetris.
Just in sadness and walking away.
I've only just watched her play and been like: "you're still playing Tetris?!"
When we were talking about this, I was like: "have you even played Tetris?"
And she was like: "Yes! Like hello... I had...," and like, listed off the games of her childhood.
People who know Dana very well are like, they've known about her... situation for a long time, they know that she's really good at --
"Her situation... my condition!"
- Her condition! To me, kind of is a condition...
What would be the best thing would be if like, when I max-out, if the Nintendo or the TV would just like... explode.
That would be awesome!
What will happen if you max it out, Dana?
Are you still gonna play Tetris?
- I think so, yeah.
As much as you play Tetris now?
Um... I mean...
I think I'll always play Tetris.
Your controller felt a little worn-out to me.
Um, they tend to get...  it's sort of a mushy feeling
- Yeah. They get mushy.
I mean, that's everyone's favorite part of the Harry preview is they're taking apart his controller
And his controller was the most mushy...
Well, it's probably 'cause he he presses so hard.
Yeah.
Doesn't he loop something? I remember seeing...
- Yeah, he like plays through his T-shirt or a T-shirt, like this...
Right.
I use a shirt on my left hand 'cause the d-pad it's... too stiff, I mean, too rough
He loops his thumb through... something.
- Which I tried by the way, after I saw that because, like, "What is he doing?!"
And then I tried it and it was like: "eh... I can play like that, but I don't need to"
Why does he do that?
'Cause it's... so his thumb doesn't hurt
Oh...
'Cause he presses so hard
All my controllers are messed up... yeah.
How much... how many you went through? Like, three or four?
Three or four, yeah, like four maybe
When he wasn't getting the record, he would blame the controller
No, no. But then that was legit.
I know! I know it's legit but I... at the time I was like "this is not legit", alright?
You're just blaming the controller
Never words of encouragement, it's always discouragement
It was like, "Hey Harry? You'll never get it..."
- All the time...
But then, to him, that's him trying to encourage me
- But to me... I felt like that was the motivation
I just remember that one time where he had a... I think it was 979,000  and he totally choked.
He had it! He had it! It was right there, and he choked... and I just laughed at his face.
He did say that, once he gets the record, he will never touch Tetris ever again
He did say that. Did you not say that?
Yeah, I did.
Yeah, he told all of us, all of his friends --
But then, that was my motivation to like... 'cause I wanted to end it, you know?
I wanted to just be done with it and...
No, so for a while he didn't play and then he started playing this internet Tetris
It's not Tetris, not Nintendo Tetris
- It was Tetris Friends, yeah.
It was like Tetris online and I called him out. I was like "what are you doing?"
I thought you were done with Tetris! "This isn't Nintendo Tetris, this is Tetris with friends" or something
What? It was Tetris Friends, man. OK, OK, wow...
- Yeah, Tetris Friends.
And then, slowly it started progressing and eventually...
I went back.
- He went back to playing Tetris.
Yeah, if I start feeling, like, physical discomfort from playing Tetris, I usually try to stop.
That's probably a good policy.
What if your girlfriend yells at you, like...
I stop then too...
- Liar.
Unless, I'm like, unless I have a really great game going, I stop.
We have a different version of that.
What's your version?
That you don't stop.
That I just keep playing until the crack of dawn?
- You say "one more game." And it's always "one more game."
- You say "one more game."
And it's always "one more game."
Redondo Beach, California
We're actually a mortgage banker, which means that we fund our own loans
1st Los Angeles Mortgage Corporation
My real talent is business card throwing. I have one stuck in the ceiling
I don't know why but I have like this kind of ritual things I do
And so I kinda flicked it and stuck one up there
I like to think Tetris had something to do with that...
Jonas always wanted to be some kind of prodigy, I know he always used to scold us
"Why didn't you get me a piano and make me practice every day, I could have been a prodigy"
"I could have been a Beethoven," you know.
- I know... This is factually correct.
My mom can't watch me play Tetris... she gets too stressed out with the speed and
if it really gets like, close, she gets more stressed than I do
Yeah, well, I was worried it was gonna bother him and make him mess up, you know,
and if he does, I'm like "Aw! It's all my fault! I shouldn't have looked at --"
I can't watch... but yeah, I don't wanna be the smother mother, you know
which is tempting when you got somebody like Jonas
The reason I think that perfectionists actually don't play the best Tetris
is that you have to kinda be sloppy.
If I was hung up on how nice and pretty the boards looked,
I don't think I'd be as good, as I am.
- Yeah.
That's where you pick after your dad, 'cause he was, you know, a real messy guy.
When it was competitive, he didn't like to watch me.
He scored pretty well, I think his highest games were about 200,000
and when I was like 10 or 11 I was scoring around then
and then I kinda left him in the dust, unfortunately.
And so there's a period where he took that personally.
Once it got ridiculous, he started coming back and watching it
and with my uncle, too, both of them -- his brother, liked to watch it quite a bit.
He was actually diagnosed with cancer 16 months before he passed.
We had a long window to just kinda work things out
and we spent a lot of days just talking, having great, you know,
philosophical, deep, wonderful discussions while us playing Tetris.
I remember the first time that I watched Jonas play.
I came here, it was - we were in high school -- and I'm watching
and I was like "Dude, Jonas is really good at Tetris."
And I've just started seeing more and more little moves --
if you play enough Tetris, you get to see like, that he flipped it
right at the very last possible second, the only moment it worked.
And I asked him, I was like "How do you do it," you know, "How is this..." --
'cause I can't think of it that fast and he goes
"You have to see the next piece coming and imagine -- like, when I'm placing this piece,
I'm actually thinking about where the next one is already going."
The master's primary consideration is the next piece
which, along with the piece in play,
allows for over 500 possible combinations of moves at any given moment.
There are always many bad moves and very few good ones.
Limited to a single piece preview the perfect moves are unknowable.
The master has an agile mind,
rejects the notion of bad luck,
welcomes the piece that does not fit,
takes calculated risks,
never gambles,
remains calm in the face of death.
The one trick to training Tetris is to be always almost dead.
If you're almost dead, you're probably training.
21 días para el torneo.
Robin is about to head south to Los Angeles
where he'll make his final preparations for the tournament.
Two years ago, if you brought up the Nintendo World Championships,
it was like, sort of a novelty, a piece of trivia about me.
If I was in a bar and my friend would be like
"You know, this guy is a Nintendo world champion."
The person he was talking to would always say, "Oh! Is it like 'The Wizard?"
And I'd be like "Yeah, that was actually -- The Wizard was made to sort of promote it."
It went from just like this funny little tidbit to me finding "Nintendo Age."
Their editor for their e-zine asked me to write some articles, which I did,
and it was really nice to like have, you know, a couple thousand people reading my story
and it was like I was getting a little touch of fame that I didn't get when it actually happened.
Robin stops in Sunnyvale, California to visit one of his old competitive gaming buddies.
He hopes to get some help running his Tetris tournament.
These are thumbs genetically designed to dominate video games.
These are massive, and they're born to win.
Chris Tang / Former Dance Dance Revolution Champion / Former Street Fighter II Champion / Los Angeles Nintendo World Champion / Sega World Champion
Actually I found the newspaper article of my first game contest which was...
the Hawaii State Nintendo Championships
and the game was Super Mario Bros. 1.
I was the only one who beat the game, 250,000 something points,
I had like four minutes left, I just sit back, relaxed,
watched everybody else dying on world 8-3,
but, you know, I was a kid at the time and I was like "Wow, I'm actually good at something,"
Robin and Chris at the Nintendo World Championships
you know, all this time I've been spending playing video games,
you know, it was not for nothing, you know, I've proven it.
That prepared me for "Rock the Rock" which is the biggest game contest,
you know, that they had on TV, $25,000 contest.
And right now is the battlefield for all the game masters to get busy on Sonic & Knuckles
for the $25,000 big daddy prize.
I did this thing where I closed my eyes and I played the game in my mind
and I guess I freaked out a lot of people which is a good thing.
Yes, he got it!
The Sega World Champion!
There you go, thanks.
There you go.
You know, this is it, this is really awesome,
I'm becoming this larger than life video game star
and I'm becoming like Robin Mihara which was the guy I thought like,
this is the guy I wanna be when I grow up. I wanna be that cool kid.
With the hat, the finger and he's got confidence
and he looks good, he plays good,
Robin defeating Chris at the Oakland NWC.
you know, stone cold, just destroying everything in his path
and I was finally living up to that example.
(al teléfono con Thor)
Hey man.
If you just get to 30,
you're gonna have to pass out some Depends, 'cause we're all gonna be peeing.
Don't let that scare you though, please, please do, anyway.
But, I know that already people are doubting him,
because he doesn't have any video tapes.
He really -- I sincerely believe he does not want the spotlight ever again,
because he feels like it kind of was the -- I forgot how he phrased it --
like the cornerstone of a very difficult life.
I had always wondered, you know, what would happen if you and Thor were face-to-face.
Yeah.
- Who would win, basically.
Thor was saying he wasn't gonna compete.
Like, he was gonna come, but he wasn't gonna compete.
So I found him on Facebook, got into a little bit of why he doesn't wanna win again.
I think there was a, sort of a failed negotiation with Nintendo.
He was kind of getting pimped out, like, his dad would drive him to trade shows
and Consumer Electronic Show.
And I don't know if he would speak for money or what he was doing exactly,
but it sounded like Thor didn't get any of it.
I don't know, maybe it's also just annoying to be known as the Tetris champion.
Being a pretty big student of the game,
I'm really excited about meeting all of these people
and seeing their different styles and personalities.
Most of these people I'm guessing just played by themselves in front of a TV
and didn't even know that other people were doing the same thing until they found Twin Galaxies.
So I want to meet them all and learn their tricks and just talk about Tetris.
It's gonna be exciting for all of us to be able to talk to somebody
who really understands the high level of the game.
Yup. Right. Burn. Right. Straight down. Right.
I can read your mind.
Totally closed my eyes for that one.
Can you talk when you're on 19?
Oh yeah, I love to talk when I'm on 19.
The stuff that you do is different, it's like you can see --
That is so crazy what you just did, that was insane.
- I'm nuts!
You put both of them just wrong and then it was fine.
Yeah. Isn't it gorgeous?
So what are you seeing when you did that?
Like, you're seeing the level above it, you don't care about -
Yeah, you kind of just see - it's just like in chess seeing a few moves ahead.
Yeah.
- Like, you create a hole and it's gone.
It's just a - you think of it as a combination.
I noticed for your record game you're stacking on this side.
Yeah. I don't know, for some reason I usually score higher on average when I stack to the right.
Oh shit.
Nice.
Phew, that's it.
You're a one-button player!
What do you mean?
You only flip one direction.
I have never played any other way.
That is crazy. Like, some of your flips are like, right before it lands.
I have never even heard of not being a one-way flipper.
This might be one of those breakthrough moments we spoke of earlier.
"And then these guys came over and they showed me that you could actually
flip the pieces in more than one direction. When all these years..."
- You've never thought to even just try this button?
I just thought it did the same thing!
Yeah, 'cause most - I think every piece... it's only three pieces...
- I was always like "why would you use B when you could use A?"
Now, I have a hard time setting this up...
OK, here we go. So this is a t-spin.
I rotated and it just went right in there.
Dude, I've never done a t-spin. Not even accidentally.
- You've never seen that?
This is pretty big. I didn't know about a million things that you just told me.
Do you guys think I'm stupid?
No, not whatsoever, I mean I spent -- this has been like a year of my life figuring this stuff out, and then...
Yeah, but this has been like, I've been playing Tetris for like 20 years.
I don't even wanna know how many hours I played Tetris. Like, that would just
depress me to know.
There's some things that I've studied in your games or the couple that I've seen;
you have a few things that no one else does.
Wow, you do that all on purpose?
I saw it develop.
The L-blocks can be flipped all over the place, a little like, little L-block flips like that,
just getting around. So, that right there, I'm gonna -- there we go.
Ooh! Damn!
I have never seen anybody do that.
But he actually did it clean like, with a purpose. That was awesome.
I can stamp it. And I had just gotten Tetris and I wasn't thinking about playing,
I was just kind of playing -- you know, nine or ten years old or whatever --
and I put up like 175,000 or whatever. I tripled my highest score since then, it was just kind of like, an epiphany.
And ever since then I've just been kind of trying to relegate the play to the back of the mind.
I play better when I hum a song to myself, random daydreaming, while I'm playing.
I almost believe that the mind kind of has like a little, like a buffering,
a kind of RAM situation, and so if you think about a move too much, your next move suffers.
Like there's a loading screen for the mind and I've definitely tested mine mad.
The heart rate starts increasing, at one point I started getting like tunnel vision.
I thought I was like about to pass out. Playing that many hours you got to think stuff,
you just think random weird things. When I was little, I just figured there was a little electronic dwarves
in the system and they were just, you know, sadistic in the way that they gave me pieces.
And that was my first concept of a tetris god.
So there's a little bit of a give-and-take war with the game itself.
Sometimes you have to concede to it. It is very difficult to fight the game, because it will win.
Sometimes I really do think it has a mind of its own.
You have to think four of five steps ahead in one second.
When I'm in the zone, it goes like, I'm pretty much like, one with the game, in sync,
just flowing.
It's like a constant flow. You're just doing this thing and like, things are changing,
it's really fluid and it just is always like, morphing into a new thing that you're just constantly reacting to.
When you're playing Tetris, just put stuff where it fits. It's that simple.
In 2002, computer scientists at MIT proved that Tetris was an NP-complete problem.
Translation: A computer cannot be programmed to find the perfect moves during a game of Tetris.
The definition of NP-complete is basically that with the input size of the problem,
the time required to calculate the answer basically increases faster than polynomial time.
With a problem like Tetris it will become longer than we like, humanly have on this earth
to even like, calculate the perfect answer.
This is Tetris Grand Master, it came out in 1998. I think I first played back when I saw --
it was one of those videos that went around on YouTube, it was I think
"Tetris Japan Finals" or something that it was labeled as -- it was a Death mode video.
Then I just thought that was really cool. It looks really challenging, it looks really fun.
Tetris: The Grand Master 2, a Japanese arcade game,
awards Grand Master status to players who can survive invisible Tetris for at least one minute.
In invisible Tetris, the pieces disappear once they'd land. Alex is one of only 30 Grand Masters in the world.
I got to the invisible credit roll and somehow managed to survive for long enough to
actually pull it together and get the grade. You have to learn the game all over at a deeper level
Alex's Grand Master game / Tetris: The Grand Master 2
in order to succeed, where you have to like... really know how is this piece affecting the stack
and that you have to keep track of like... how can I keep the stack easy to remember.
I just hope that I can, you know, play pretty consistently, I don't have like a bad day or something.
I don't have many other expectations for myself other than that, just to
go and have a good time playing some NES Tetris.
Nintendo Tetris allows the player to start on any level up to 19.
Starting on 19 is the only way to train to become a master.
The basic thing you gotta do when you train is you do level 19 and you try to tetris, constantly.
You'll fail, because it's fast.
In NES Tetris or Nintendo Tetris the speed plateaus for 10 levels at a speed that seems
impossible to most players. One split second of extra thought is equal to your death.
At Level 19, the game reaches a punishing speed.
The pieces begin to fall as though the player were constantly pushing down,
taking less than 2/3 of a second to reach the bottom.
The Tetris Master can only survive by taking control of the piece during its brief entry delay:
...the 1/6 of a second between one piece landing and the next appearing at the top.
Right when I know the piece is done, I'm already pressing the D-pad,
so by the time it comes out, it's already moving in that direction.
Once you get past the panic and you realize that you're probably pushing way too hard
on the buttons, I try really hard to shift into my peripheral vision,
'cause if you focus too hard on the actual screen, I find that that flusters me.
It really makes a sort of a radical certainty the only way to go.
It's better to put a piece in the wrong place than to change your mind and try to put it
in the right place. So you have to go with your first instinct and you have to have
the software in your brain to make that first place you think of the right place.
Last time I got Tetris Effect was when I was -- shoot. I was in high school.
The Tetris Effect refers to players having dreams or mild hallucinations about the game.
I was doing some specialty stacking like, there's something that Sega Tetris players used to do.
They would draw a pattern in the stack, they would leave holes
to make a greater-than shape in the stack.
And so, the last time I got Tetris Effect really bad is when I started doing that
and I did it for like, an hour or something the first day.
And the next day I was just like, wanted to kill myself,
'cause I couldn't stop thinking about making the staircase and like,
putting all the pieces down. Because it was something --
it was a totally new problem for my brain to consider.
When I have a square or rectangle shape or a box of any sort and
I need to put things into it -- it goes back to -- that's what everybody calls it,
they say "Jesse, you're tetrisizing!"
I daydream during the day, I'll sit and play Tetris in my head,
I have Tetris dreams at night sometimes, you know, if I'm playing it right before I go to bed.
There was a very interesting study by some guys at Harvard who were studying sleep.
And they did have people play Tetris before they went to bed and sure enough:
They often dreamed about Tetris.
And the researchers came to the general conclusion from this and other data
that one of the purposes of dreaming is memory consolidation
of things you've learned during the day.
In 1992, Dr. Haier used brain scans to show that Tetris training can lead to increased brain efficiency.
The brains of people struggling to learn the game showed high level of activity,
indicated here on the brain scan in red.
But the brains of the players who have mastered the game showed very little activity and appeared to be at rest.
Now, of course on the second scan the game is faster, the game is harder, they're processing more.
And the question for us was: Is the brain more or less active?
Virtually everyone assumed the brain had to be more active.
We had thought the brain actually might be more efficient
as the Tetris program became unconscious and automatic
and would require less activity, less energy.
And sure enough that's what we found.
That software -- so to speak -- in your brain can become very powerful.
So much as you can get out of its way you can become...
when you're playing, when you calm yourself down enough, like a human computer.
7 días para el torneo.
You would not believe, I walk around in this T-shirt all the time --
no one gets it. No one gets it. Like, guys, really?
To go along with it: my Nintendo pants!
We have "Mario is my homeboy," "Classically trained"
with the original Nintendo controller.
So, this will be my official competition outfit.
Just being at the competition like, I am so stoked about that that all I wanna do
is just go play with these guys, you know, these guys that are great.
The tournament as I understand it basically is three games and you...
the highest score gets into the finals. It's really gonna come down to:
Who can survive to level 29? 'Cause that's gonna give you another 200,000 points.
So if I just survive to level 29, I will beat most of the people
who traditionally are... -- have lower scores than me.
Like players like Jesse and Ben, they will... I mean, I know they will play safe already.
I might just get a bad set of pieces, you never know, so I think...
playing a little safe will be the best bet.
It's gonna kinda be a balance. I'm gonna try to tetris,
but try to do it in such a way that I don't kill myself.
I've kinda designed it to score consistently. I don't wanna put down a 400,000.
That's -- if you see me put down a 400,000, like, hide the sharp objects.
I'm hoping on Sunday it'll be over. Like, you know, ...
I don't expect anything less than, you know, victory, so...
Yeah, maybe I shouldn't have said that, but OK.
Yeah, well, I'll guarantee the finals.
So, you asked about Jonas, but you haven't asked about Thor.
You have any questions about him?
- ...from what I heard he's not playing?
Uh, actually... we think he's going to make an appearance. He's definitely...
Appearance as in like... participating, or...?
- ...and compete, yeah.
Guess who's showing up tonight?
And he's going to be in the tournament... man...
- Uh yes... Sorry, I didn't tell you?
No, I mean, last I knew I thought he wasn't going to be.
I just... I feel almost annoyed that Thor hasn't done anything in the way of proving what he has done.
He recently had a Facebook update, "just got to a million points a Level 30 for the first time in 20 years."
You got a cellphone! At least take a cellphone picture, or something!
He finally broke out his Nintendo and he says that he uh... he got to 30, Level 30.
He says that he's actually got to 30!?
That's what he says!
- ...oh my god...
He says that it like killed his thumbs.
But it has never been on tape.
Yeah, I mean, if you recorded it and showed it to someone...
- No photos...
...'cause I'm always like...
- Skeptical.
Yeah, the whole... past Level 30 thing...
I can't imagine it. Unless... unless he's like...
you know, a finger tapping god, but even with that,
I don't think he could maneuver
that well to get rid of 20+ pieces
in that speed. I mean that's what I think,
but, you know what, honestly... what, we're like five days away?
I mean, I really hope Thor proves me wrong.
Robin has just found out that Thor has finally arrived.
Great.
They've agreed to meet for the first time in 20 years
here at the production's homebase in Laguna Beach, California.
Where is he?
[smalltalk not audible]
20 years later! You've turned into a man!
How you doing?
- We've both grown a little bit!
Yeah, yeah.
[smalltalk]
I mean you're out of it, right?
...you have all these people like, whispering about you
and, you know, the fact that you don't have it taped just infuriates them.
They're like, why wouldn't he tape it if he can get to 30?
That's kinda my idea in some ways.
Do you feel any responsibility to like... people that like see this game as a "religion?"
To like, just show what is possibile?
I had a massive accident in '96.
You know, they took a big chunk of my skull out because it was all rammed into my brain.
I was in a coma for a while.
Do you think that affected your game at all?
Oh yeah, it affected everything.
Sometimes, you know, things are just blank in my head.
It's an honor to actually meet some of them popping up here today,
like Thor Aackerlund and Ben Mullen.
People I've just heard the names of, read the legends of, seen... random forum posts from,
and now seeing them live to life, it's... wow.
Like... a mortal walking amongst gods.
I don't know what to do with myself!
other than snap pictures and humbly stay away unless they beckon me.
With Kelly handy, Robin decides to attempt a world record on Tengen Tetris.
Ben Mullen currently holds the world record with a score 1.89 million.
A record on Tengen Tetris is known as a "marathon,"
because the difficulty plateaus at a sustainable level.
Robin has been playing for about one hour.
He's already flipped the score once so he's at... 1.84
Wait, wait, wait.
Ohh!?
There it is!
*applause*
Oh, wait wait wait, let's see the high score on the screen here.
[something] touch it?
Having been reluctant to play any Tetris since arriving, Thor suddenly decides to break both records.
We gotta get Kelly, uh, Thor's about to break the world record now.
How many times have you flipped it?
- Just once.
It takes a long time to flip it just once.
Thor, thank you for allowing my record to stand for three hours.
What is... I don't even know what my record is!
11...
1238! Nice! Ah, he'll never get there.
Let me tell you the story of the signing of the Treaty of Versailles.
It all began with World War I...
Thor has been playing for over two hours.
He has smashed both world records.
Suicide!
Congratulations!
Good work, Thor.
Good game, Thor.
He's done!
You broke both records.
So, Thor, you just broke the Tengen record -- was that something you saw yourself trying before you got here?
No, it just looked like fun.
Was it a game you'd ever played before?
Yeah, it was actually the one that I could rent, so I practiced that.
So, I didn't have a Nintendo. My friend Aaron did.
I was out of school by then. My last school was in 5th grade.
So I'd hang out with him, he was one of the only people I knew in the neighborhood,
and he had a Nintendo Power thing, and it was talking about NWC.
His parents took him down there and they took me with them.
It was fun, because, socially I didn't have much exposure to anything,
because I was either at home or had like two friends.
Um... My house had burned down in '89, and my mom was in the hospital for a long time.
She had an attack of something called ventricular fibrillation,
it's a kind of tachycardia attack, where your heart tries to pump too fast from the signals.
She had a lot of facial paralysis, like a stroke victim,
and uh... so that was pretty hard on us.
So my dad um... wasn't really having any income, and my mom was unable to work,
and... just being able to get the prizes was helpful.
We've got some big winnings tonight: $10,000 US saving bond, a large screen Panasonic TV,
a pair of Reeboks, you can keep those,
and a brand new Geo LSI convertible.
Like, I wanted to give the car to my brother but we had to sell it...
um... we had to cash the savings bond in and all this other stuff.
So, it was more like relief than anything else.
It's been a long trip, but I'm glad it's over,
but I'm glad I won, too.
I didn't really have anything left over from the fire,
but I did have a little metal box that survived,
and what was in it but Micro Machines!
And then in a couple years I would be endorsing the video game.
Micro Machines for Nintendo is one of the best and most innovative racing games ever.
From there I had a short career endorsing things, and my family had a lot of financial difficulties,
and for a while -- this is interesting, but -- my income from um...
the NWC and the endorsements -- for several years -- was the only income my family had.
And, you know, we basically became... pretty much almost homeless.
It left me with a really bitter feeling.
I think you could make a lot of parallels with life philosophy that way,
because life isn't fair, and all Tetris sure isn't fair --
you gotta deal with what they give you, and sometimes they give you some really hard to swallow garbage, but,
you know... if you can chug through it that makes you a winner.
Robin has invited the Tetris Masters to meet up in Laguna Beach.
For most of them, it is their first time meeting in person.
I'm gonna give Harry a call. You wanna call Harry? Say, "where are you?"
Robin was worried you might have chickened out because you were afraid of me, but...
Oh, I didn't get your name, that's why. Oh, good to finally meet you!
Alex; nice to meet you!
- Jonas; it's a pleasure, man.
What's up, yo!
Good to meet you!
- You too, man!
[indistinct chatter]
We hung out at a mall and played Mortal Kombat for a couple hours.
I can't really imagine a person being too much better than Jonas.
Yeah, I've been watching him, he's just about as good as it can get.
I'm hurting right now
It's because Jonas scored that high, that's why.
It bothers me.
You know, the Tetris players that are here right now
are going to shatter any possible idea of what people thought could be obtained in Tetris.
Dain Anderson / Founder, NintendoAge.com
I used to play the original arcade version,
and I used to bet money with the guys in my high school.
Whoever could hold the reins -- you know, King of the Hill in the arcade --
the longest, was sort of, you know, the unspoken god of Tetris, and
you know, I was that guy, and to come here and see these guys
just wax the floor with me... It's sort of a level of inhuman.
It's moving faster than onlookers can actually perceive the game.
These guys are thinking it. You know, they're thinking pieces ahead,
and make sure they have platforms ready for the next piece.
You know, it's really something to watch. I think that any one can appreciate Tetris at that level.
The Tetris community is a phenomenal community, and it just needs to be exposed to the world,
the world to see, yeah, it's not just a game, it's... a history. It's an evolution.
You kind of like... shake the whole controller with you
- It's not just your thumb.
Yeah, it's the controller.
- Kind of like a drum... like a high school drum major.
That's it. Exactly, exactly, exactly.
- Nice.
Because you had been to Level 30.
Which I haven't even flirted with, I think.
Yeah, I think all of us, that's kind of the white elephant in the room is that... we want to see it.
I'll give it my best.
It's something that I probably won't see but I will watch in like, reverence.
I was watching you earlier -- I think that you could definitely do it
almost... immediately if you do the center well.
The center well?
- Yeah
Call
One down, one up.
[???] (Flop?)
[???]
Survey says...
Stick a white in there, Kelly.
If you want to stay...
All of a sudden I'm just looking like... wow,
I'm up against Robin, he's destroying everyone.
He's wanting to push it all-in hard.
You only live once. I push in, figured, why not.
...cherry coke. Trips.
So do I... King high!
Boom baby! Boom! That's right, now you're in my house bitch!
Yeah!
[???] (Is ??? taping?)
I couldn't contain my excitement. It was an absolutely incredible moment.
Kind of felt like some basketball player that goes up to the hoop, --
boom! -- dunks on Shaquille O'Neal. Take that!
That's right, it's my home now!
Somebody's gonna like, pull a Tonya Harding and break everybody's thumbs...
and they're like the only one left.
If anyone would do that here I think it would be Ben.
Yeah, I've already actually broken Harry's, he's on the way to the doctor right now.
So, you don't do... you don't do the two buttons yet... that's --
- Well, I do now.
I think... Harry's 808 video online doesn't use both buttons.
- Yeah. He and I talked about it.
I actually noticed that Harry builds on the left side, which is interesting.
I build on the left...
- I feel the right side.
I find that to be unacceptable.
DANA: You mean you leave your... leave your slot on the right?
BEN: I mean, it works for him, but I would not do that.
JONAS: Yeah, I leave the well on the right.
Who said it was unacceptable to... to the left? It was you?
No, you see, for my level 19+ game?
No, I know that you...
I switch back, yeah.
The reason I did it to the left, the gap on the left? Is because I score higher when I go to the left.
[???]
Yeah, I've done it. Because back in the day I used to play hours and hours and hours,
and leaving the gap... yeah.
Good luck tomorrow, Ben, good luck.
- Thank you Harry!
You're awesome man, you're awesome.
- I actually really appreciate that.
You're awesome too, you know that?
Why thank you!
There are eight spots in the semi-finals.
Five are reserved for players who hold previous world records
Those players are Jonas, Harry, Jesse, Ben and Thor.
The remaining three spots are open to the public
The preliminary round is unlimited attempts at high-score on Type-B Tetris, with a 25 line limit.
Seven tetrises are possible within the 25 lines.
Dana, Alex and Trey all must qualify to reach the semis.
They'll have from noon until 2PM to post a high-score.
I'm not gonna wish him luck.
She doesn't even like me, she doesn't want me to win
- It's gotta be skill!
But I expect to win on skill, not on luck.
Yeah. Uh... this is my mother, Doris.
Hello!
She's the best mom a Tetris player can have.
I'm about nervous enough to throw up, because everyone I know is expecting me to win.
There are some times when you're just in "The Zone." You know where to put every piece.
You know what that's gonna leave you with.
Anyway, I came out here from New York. I'm just hoping to make it to the semi rounds.
Maybe be like the underdog or something.
I think the highest you can get is seven tetrises and then at that point, you've hit the... sort of the 25 line limit
And the game ends. So I think it would be cool to play in the semi-finals
Although I know I'll just get destroyed there.
Nah, I think I'm number 2 now, but not for long.
Did Alex get it?
So no one's done it. No one's done the perfect.
Nope, not yet.
-Door still open
Eventually I think people are gonna get perfect ones.
I think the best right now is 147 [thousand]
So it's gonna get like --
And then it comes down to the pushing it down
- And then it comes down to the push down!
167,759.
How did it feel?
Good! After all those really bad games, I just got one where everything was clean and didn't push it too hard.
And I just like... went for the tetrises and they all just came together.
So, that was good.
There was a move at the end where I saw I had to make a hole
but I saw it was above the fourth row, it was at the sixth row and I was on my last tetris
I was like "thank goodness," 'cause I could like make that hole, not worry about it
complete the rows that I needed and I just like, went for it.
Just a few minutes ago, I got it, I finally got it. I got the seven in a row. So I should be able to make it through with that.
There's about four or five people who could probably match that and then it's all about how many times you've pushed down to get a few extra points.
I don't think it's gonna be like, where two or three are just gonna like come in and like get perfect games
and like push me out. I think have a spot.
How are you feeling, Trey?
Uh... well my heart is pounding now, but during the game I was just like...
You know, either I'll get the pieces or I won't get the pieces.
I figured: if I just keep playing, eventually I'll just get seven in a row. I did.
Trey is now in first with 167,911 making it all level 18, seven tetrises and pretty much,
pushing down on the d-pad to get extra points is separating the top three scores at this point.
Dana is still in there.
I'm not doing as well as I can do so... it's a little bit disappointing
but hopefully I can, you know, pull it together
She's usually even-keeled for the most part and so... um, it kinda surprises me that she's having such a hard time right now
Dana is one of the most kick-ass people I know.
She's like a gamer at heart. She and Brook are just meant for each other.
I don't know, I think girls in gaming adds a really really valuable perspective for you know...
A male dominated nerd-fest, you know?
I think that she's under the most pressure of anybody here, 'cause the cameras are following her
She keeps getting interviewed by newspapers and I kinda feel bad for her
1:42 PM / Eighteen minutes left to qualify.
because it's like... a lot of added pressure that... it's obviously affecting her
Ah! What happened?!
Aw, man!
Sorry to get pissed
God, it's giving me heart palpitations just to watch this.
Dana is one Tetris away from a perfect seven.
Dana is forced to burn off her last line, just as she receives the necessary long bar
Fuck me! Aw man!!
Holy fuck!
Yeah, like, it would've been better if it didn't even...
If it didn't show up.
Yeah, if it didn't even show.
I've been really close to seven, twice.
I can get seven.
One Tetris away from perfect.
With one line left to go.
Is she in?
Am I in?
She did it.
Fuck yeah!
Pepito Pea / Acupunturista de Dana
How are you feeling?
Fucking awesome!!
Dana just edged out her friend Alex for the last spot.
Oh, I think I'm in 4th right now.
It might just be that I got knocked out.
He's so cute. He's the little baby Grand Master.
[indistinct chatter]
Hey, guys.
Hey, congratulations.
Thank you, Alex.
Top 3. It's official.
And we have our top 8 for the finals.
Hello everybody, hello Tetris fans and champions.
Welcome to Tetris competition.
I'm Alexey Pajitnov. I am creator of the game.
I hope that everybody here will have a wonderful time, and good luck to everyone.
So, when I first met Alexey in 1989, it was February of 1989.
He said to me: "Henk, you know, you're gonna go back and you're gonna make this game and...
I really wanna find out who's the best player in the world."
And I, you know, we really haven't found out, in all these years.
And the very interesting thing about all this, is Robin is the guy who's been putting this tournament together
and we really need to give him a hand in making this Tetris World Championships possible.
It comes from his passion and from life experiences; how Tetris and the Nintendo World Championships changed his life
uh... that now we're having this wonderful Tetris Classic World Championship
Alright! It is now time for our semi-finals, eight players will compete in three rounds.
Round 1 will be an attempt for the most lines
And Round 2 and 3 will be an attempt for the most points.
And the top two players will advance to our Tetris finals.
Alright, let's start in ten, nine, eight, seven, six, five, four, three, two, one... Let's play some Tetris!
Alright, we start off here...
Harry gets a triple line score, followed by another I believe.
Looks like Jesse... is out!
- Jesse has topped out.
52,541!
Thor setting up, he's got his well set, just needs a long block.
...as we switch to Thor.
Thor looks like --
Thor is out with 89 lines!
- Thor Aackerlund has topped out!
The audience is shocked by Thor's early top-out.
He'll have to dominate the score rounds to have any chance to make the finals.
And remember, at Level 29 the speed increases again, believe it or not,
what's known as the kill-screen, or death level.
- We're getting close to the kill-screen here at Level 28.
290, and here it is!
- Jonas is at 278... Look at that speed! Harry at 290!
Harry is out! 290 for Harry!
- Harry 290!
- That's the leader right now!
Jonas at 281, can he hit 290?
Dana was out -- I don't know where Dana was out, but Dana's out.
...261, let's go to the other screen.
Let's switch the video back to... there we go.
Alright.
- Jonas, 29!
294! 294 for Jonas, that's our leader!
Jonas scores 294 lines, the second most in recorded history.
Ben at 2 -- there's two players left -- Ben at 280!
But this is a good score as well, it looks like it'll be in the top three for sure.
Single line Ben, oh here we go!
Ben, 290 as well! Great job guys!
Jonas, Ben, and Harry all succeed at reaching the Level 29 kill-screen.
Matt and Dana post decent scores while the rest lag behind.
...second looks like... tie for second is Harry and Ben!
...four, three, two, one,
Go!
- Let's play some Tetris!
Now, we will be looking for lots of tetrises here.
Dana... Dana is trying to work out, she's working it.
Dana is doing good to survive there, awesome burning Dana!
She's got there, she's burning off, she's waiting for a long -- there it is!
Tetris!
- That's good for a tetris!
Triple line score for Thor right there.
- Jonas is in the lead right now.
134 for Jonas, 122... Harry, Thor -- 99 thousand.
Ben... setting up for a tetris!
Boom! Tetris for Harry!
- A tetris for Harry as well! And Thor with a tetris!
Thor burns a double line right there, he's waiting for a long piece...
Here it comes, tetris! 207 for Thor!
Tetris for Harry!
- 343 for Harry, wow.
The leader is going to be... it looks like Jonas is going to be the leader of this one.
[something about Ben's loss]
Ben is out! With 249,919.
Thor with a tetris!
Dana needs a long piece... Dana gets it!
Triple line score for Dana.
Dana in trouble! She slides an L...
Dana's out! Dana with 363,824!
Double line for Jonas...
Harry's at 19, the end is near.
He's going to come away with...
Harry with 451,615 -- that's the current leader, but not for long.
Level 19...
- 348 for Thor, he just slides a long block.
Oh! Jonas is out! 453,378!
Jonas is now Top 4, followed by Harry.
We're down to just two players: Matt and Thor!
Matt... stayin' alive here.
Matt is... Matt is out! 421,146, now for Thor,
Thor is remaining here. I believe Thor has the lead for the round!
Thor! Vibrate your thumb dude!
His vibrating thumbs are the _only_ thing that can keep you alive here!
And Thor is out! 469,454!
Thor narrowly wins round two, but it's not quite enough to put him back in the race for the finals.
Did a lot better this round -- you went from next to last to first, I believe.
I'm surrounded by greatness.
Greatness makes you great.
451, not bad, you were the leader for a while
I'll do better.
He'll do better!
Jonas, 453 -- you could have done a little bit better, or...?
Uh, I feel inside that I have a Tetris monster within me, and...
Unleash it! Unleash that monster, Jonas!
I'm just going to let it out next game.
I'm just going to open the cage door and see what happens.
The leaders right now -- wow, it's close.
In first is Jonas Neubauer with 196.6 points...
The top five scores are close. A weak game from Harry or Jonas in round three could give Dana or Matt a chance to make the finals.
It would take a near max-out score for Ben or Thor to sneak in.
Three, two, one,
Go!
- Tetris time!
Again, points matter. So we're going to be looking for lots of strategy to get those tetrises.
[some stuff????]
Ben burns off a double and follows with a tetris, beautiful, and another tetris for Ben! 221!
[indistinct]
Matt and Dana are keeping a good pace to challenge Harry and Jonas.
Dana is living a little dangerously now.
Another tetris for Dana, 191.
But mid-way through round three, Harry and Jonas are showing no signs of letting up.
...setting up for another tetris, here it comes for Ben.
Ben breaches 300 thousand, Ben has 313 thousand -- I believe that's the lead.
Ben is on pace for a max-out. A score in that range would be his only chance to make the finals.
And another tetris! 345!
345 for Ben! Jonas, 302; Thor 229; Harry, 283.
Remember, the speed will stay about consistent until it hits Level 19 when the speed then jumps up.
Thor is waiting for a long block... as is Jonas, as is Ben.
Thor knocks out another one.
Ben is in a little... Ben burns off a triple line score. That was key.
Oh, Ben... Ben is in a little bit of trouble.
Oh Ben...
Ben is out!
- Oh, Ben topped out!
Ben succumbs to a 36 piece long bar drought.
Jonas is now our current leader.
Dana at 314.
Harry at 495. 431 for Jonas.
Dana is out! 484,073 for Dana!
Jonas setting up for a tetris on the right side.
Jonas slips a little bit, he gets it back a little bit... Jonas is out!
Jonas, 550,841!
Jonas tops out with a 550 thousand, leaving the door open for Matt and Thor.
Oh, Matt is in a little bit of trouble here.
He gets back a single... Trey with a single... Matt is out!
Good job Matt! Matt with 454,781.
We're down to -- Thor is out! Thor with 506,084 points.
Harry is gunning to take the lead from Jonas.
He's doing a great job of keeping it low and burning it off.
He's almost at the death-screen here. He's almost at Level 29.
Harry! Harry!
583,373!
- Awesome. Awesome play.
Harry finishes off round three by achieving the top score of the day,
of 583,000 points.
I just felt so great in that third game, and just tanked right as it...
On level 13 I think or something.
But when did you lose -- 13?
- Yeah.
Oh, man. I know how you feel right now.
You can do it, you can do it.
- Hopefully, hopefully.
I don't care which one of you wins, but...
- But Jonas is tough, Jonas is tough, so...
Oh, I know!
- ...so we'll see what happens with that
Yeah.
Alright, here we go, the top two: Harry Hong and Jonas Neubauer!
These two will be competing in the main event: the finals!
The finals are a best two out of three head-to-head match for the highest score.
Harry and Jonas made it here by playing consistent, mistake-free Tetris in the semi-finals.
Harry executes a death-defying vertical long bar slide.
But it turns out not to be enough to save him.
Harry has his first bad game of the night with a paltry 302,000 points.
Jonas wins round one, making round two a must-win situation for Harry.
Harry, come on! Let's go!
Uh-oh!
Harry, Harry, Harry! ...
- Jonas, Jonas, Jonas! ...
Harry has taken control of round 2 with a 50,000 point lead.
Harry tops out with a score of 517,000.
It's Jonas's game to lose now.
Jonas prevails, surpassing Harry's score of 517,000 with a tetris on level 23.
Jonas, Jonas, Jonas! ...
Jonas Neubauer!
World Tetris Champion!
[singing]
Congratulations!
I gotta take this time to thank my uncle Bill for bringing me to Tetris...
- Yeah, uncle Bill!
...when I was at the tender age of 10 setting me down the path of addiction.
...your 1,000 dollars!
Well, that'll just about do it for ...
I'm a little disappointed that Thor wasn't able to really show what he's capable of,
but he just had an off day.
It was fantastic being up there.
It was nerve-wracking and it was very loud and it was very hot.
It was an amazing experience, of course I wanted to win,
but Jonas, you know, he's phenomenal, so...
hopefully I'll try again next year.
I really wish I'd won today, so...
It's Tetris man, anything can happen.
- Yeah.
Turns out it's pretty random.
Yeah, who knew!
Yeah!
Tetris of all things is random.
I kinda rolled the dice a little bit and tried to set up the tetris for the win,
and I'm glad that that kinda... I'm glad that that played out.
That was ballsy!
I saw you do that, that was ballsy. I would not have done it.
I'm just saying that Thor Aackerlund of all people to die at --
I don't know how many lines he died at, but that's odd to me.
I think he wanted to be able to do well in score without having to be afraid of winning.
'Cause he didn't wanna win.
- Yeah.
He really has seemed like he doesn't want to win this tournament.
The next day, Thor attempted to reach level 30 for the cameras.
His thumbs cannot vibrate as quickly as they had in his World Championship days.
After dozens of attempts he gave up.
That first round when I totally glitched on the lines game,
I was having trouble with my controller, which -- that wasn't why I stacked up.
I stacked up because I was taking too many risks,
but the controller was distracting me.
And I mentioned this to Harry after he was done with his game
and he had brought his own controller and he still had his original
that was there, provided for his station and he's like, "Here, you can use this one."
You know, and I plugged it in and sure enough, it worked great and that's --
the very next round I got top score, so, you know,
he was really classy and friendly.
When I watched Jonas I was really worried because I kept pulling for the person I was watching,
I was going back and forth, you know, just stressing out on the edge of my seat watching the finals.
Like, at one point Jonas had this crazy, you know, like, double well,
crazy canyon looking thing with all these weird gaps
and I was like, about to pull my hair out, I was like "oh no."
I can see it - the way I was looking, I was like "you need like, these seven or eight pieces
to come in a sequence to make this work." And NES Tetris is infamously malicious,
but those pieces that he needed all came in a sequence and he locked them all together.
It's one thing for the pieces to come, but only a very select few people in the world
could take those pieces and put them where they need to go, all in a line at high speed.
So it was really impressive.
This has been an absolute honor and blast to meet all of y'all involved in this
and it's gonna be a memory that I'll cherish, you know, for decades.
Upon returning to Texas
Thor vowed to officially break or match all records on NES Tetris, in a year's time.
A few months later...
Thor starts on level 19.
Jonas is the only person known to have maxed out starting on this level.
Thor's renewed ability to vibrate his left thumb is evidenced in the rapid side-to-side movement of the pieces.
Thor is on pace to max out.
Thor prepares a center well in an attempt to survive the level 29 kill-screen.
Nivel 29.
Nivel 30.
Thor reaches every milestone achievement in NES Tetris:
max-out starting on level 19, level 30,
all in the same game.
Tu eres un maestro del Tetris